Guide to the Spencer Berger Collection on Film, Theater, and Music
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Spencer Berger Collection on film, theater, and music
1876-2000
YCAL MSS 759
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
15.55
(27 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 2 art
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Spencer Berger, stemming from his avocational interest in film, theater, and music, and from his particular research and collecting activities focused on actors John Barrymore, Lionel Barrymore, and Ethel Barrymore and musicians Ted Lewis and Leopold Stokowski. Material includes correspondence; photographs, including movie stills and autographed photographs of John Barrymore, Lionel Barrymore, Ethel Barrymore, and others; playbills, clippings, and other printed material; notes; scrapbooks; and other papers.
Berger, Spencer, 1917-2002
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Spencer Berger,1992-1996, and Eric H. Berger, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 24-25 (35mm film): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Spencer Berger (1917-2002)
Spencer Merriam Berger was a business executive and film historian. He was born on May 6, 1917 in New Haven, Connecticut, and graduated from Yale University in 1940. He served as president and chairman of the board of the former Berger Brothers Company of New Haven, which made women's and surgical corsets. He was a leading authority on the actors John, Lionel, and Ethel Barrymore, and an enthusiast of Ted Lewis and Leopold Stokowski.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created and accumulated by Spencer Berger, stemming from his avocational interest in film, theater, and music, and from his particular research and collecting activities focused on actors John Barrymore, Lionel Barrymore, and Ethel Barrymore and musicians Ted Lewis and Leopold Stokowski. Material includes correspondence; photographs, including movie stills and autographed photographs of John Barrymore, Lionel Barrymore, Ethel Barrymore, and others; playbills, clippings, and other printed material; notes; scrapbooks; and other papers.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: October 1992 Acquisition, December 1995 Acquisition, December 1996 Acquisition, and November 2007 Acquisition.
Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States; Musicians -- United States; Photographs; Audiovisual materials; Barrymore, Ethel, 1879-1959; Barrymore, John, 1882-1942; Barrymore, Lionel, 1878-1954; Berger, Spencer, 1917-2002; Lewis, Ted, 1892-1971; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977
- October 1992 Acquisition, 1960, undated; 0.21; 1 box
  - "Myself as I Think Others See Me," drafts, autograph manuscript, corrected and signed, and typescript, 1960, undated (Box 31)
- December 1995 Acquisition, 1876-1995; 5.51; (12 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 2 art
  Arrangement
  Files are not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  The December 1995 Acquisition contains correspondence, notes, photographs, scrapbooks, and printed materials, such as programs and playbills, relating to stage performances, film, and the Barrymore family. Included are correspondence between Margot Peters and Spencer Berger; autographed photographs of Warner Baxter, Marie Dressler and others; and a collection of articles relating to Vitaphone and Warner Brothers on the twentieth anniversary of talking pictures.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 468.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Spencer Berger, 1995.
  - Clippings and receipts, 1977-1993 (Box 1)
  - To-do list and clippings, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and receipts, 1979-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Newsletters and correspondence, 1914-1993 (Box 1)
  - Movie industry regarding John Barrymore, 1935-1982, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings and correspondence, 1938-1993 (Box 1)
  - Film collection: correspondence and resume, 1977-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Receipts and newsletters, 1977-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and writings, 1950-1991, undated (Box 1)
  - GSB and EHB Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Theatre programs, 1940-1961 (Box 1)
  - Photos, 1921-1969, undated (Box 1)
  - This is Tomorrow, 1937-1940 (Box 1)
  - John Barrymore estate auction, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence "H" - "L", 1944-1974 (Box 1)
  - Film books reviews, 1967-1977, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Yale, 1967-1973 (Box 1)
  - Movie lists and appliance instructions, 1987-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Laserdisc information and Barrymore, 1983-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings, correspondence and Yale, 1967-1994 (Box 1)
  - J.N. Darling correspondence, 1932 November 9 (Box 1)
  - John Barrymore sketches and engineering certificate, 1938, undated (Box 1)
  - John Barrymore placard, 1925 September (Box 1)
  - Buster Keaton autographed photo, 1939 (Box 1)
  - John Barrymore sketch 1923, 1959 October (Box 1)
  - Barrymore brothers on TIME magazine cover, 1932 March 7 (Box 1)
  - Ethel Barrymore photos and coverage, 1901-1941 (Box 1)
  - Misc. papers, 1926-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Barrymore coverage (John, Lionel and Ethel), 1927-1982 (Box 1)
  - Barrymore Hamlet, 1921-1927 (Box 1)
  - Autographed theatre programs, 1933-1936 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1969, undated (Box 1)
  - Family slides from Margy H., circa 1981 (Box 1)
  - Ted Lewis, 1920-1970 (Box 1)
  - Celebrity pictures, 1933 July, undated (Box 1)
  - Photos and etchings re: movie stars, 1925-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - John Barrymore "Writes on the Movies", 1922-1939 (Box 1)
  - Early movies, correspondence, clippings and list, 1913-1993, undated (Box 2)
  - Movie list, photos, 1989-1993 (Box 2)
  - Barrymore clippings, 1913-1993 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and notes - banks/financial and movie/CD clippings, 1912-1993, undated (Box 2)
  - List of bills to pay, 1992 September 2 (Box 2)
  - Barrymore art acquisition, 1982-1992, undated (Box 2)
  - Yale correspondence, 1940-1968 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and clippings re: movie histories, 1943-1992, undated (Box 2)
  - Laserdisc and financial reports, 1986-1993 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence re: Barrymore book, 1939-1944 (Box 2)
  - St. Thomas's Parish House playbills, 1932-1935 (Box 2)
  - Barrymore series, Pacific Film archive, 1982-1983, undated (Box 2)
  - Misc. papers and correspondence, 1933-1985 (Box 2)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1944-1993 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Margot re: Barrymore, 1964-1993 (Box 2)
  - Clippings and newsletters, 1949-1993 (Box 2)
  - Laserdisc info, 1991-1993, undated (Box 2)
  - Laserdisc mailings, 1945-1991 (Box 2)
  - Misc. mailings and newsletters, 1926-1994, undated (Box 2)
  - Cinephile and Blackhawk Film correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 2)
  - Films scrapbook, undated (Box 2)
  - Misc correspondence and clippings [Goodman?], 1974-2012 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters - Evergreen News and Yale-New Haven, 1935-1994 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence re: films, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Business update mailings, 1993, undated (Box 2)
  - Film and stage promotions, 1952-1988; 2 (Box 2)
  - Smithsonian mailings and notes, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Film and stage promotions, 1924-1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Film inventories and clippings, 1967-1995, undated (Box 2)
  - California travel information, 1958-1993, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and movie listings and information re: retirement, 1981-1994, undated (Box 2)
  - Playbills and programs, 1933-1981, undated; 12 (Box 3)
  - Playbills and programs, 1932-1978, undated; 11 (Box 4)
  - Playbills and programs, 1917-1980; 9 (Box 5)
  - Playbills and programs, 1878-1988; 10 (Box 6)
  - Playbills and programs, 1932-1977; 9 (Box 7)
  - Printed materials, 1933-1994, undated; 14 (Box 8)
  - Playbills and programs, 1919-1995; 7 (Box 9)
  - Playbills and programs relating to Barrymore family, 1876-1971; 6 (Box 10)
  - Poster - Elizabeth Love in Holiday, 1936 (Box 11 (Broadside))
  - Poster - Ethel Barrymore in Capt. Jinks of the Horse Marines, undated (Box 12 (Broadside))
  - Opera House of New Haven: Marie Gordon as That Lass O' Lowrie's, undated (Box 13 (Art))
  - Declaration of the Thirteen States of House, undated (Box 14 (Art))
  - Oversize
    - Poster - John Barrymore in 20th Century, 1934, undated (Box 15)
    - John Barrymore photos, undated (Box 15)
    - "My Reminiscences," Ethel Barrymore scrapbook, 1923-1924 (Box 15)
    - Poster - Garbo in The Secret Loves of Queen Christina, undated (Box 15)
    - Movie promos, 1917-1984; 14 (Box 16)
- December 1996 Acquisition, 1896-1992; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  The December 1996 Acquistion consists chiefly of photographs of members of the Barrymore family and others; included are photographs signed by the Barrymores, Joan Bennett, Eric Blore, George Gerswhin, Leopold Stokowski, and Lawrence Tibbett. In addition, there are movie stills and printed materials.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 511.
  Gift of Spencer Berger, 1996.
  - Photographs, 1896-1943, undated (Box 17)
  - Letter, ephemera, 1935-1975 (Box 17)
  - Ephemera, 1926-1969, undated (Box 17)
  - Signed photographs, 1930-1936, undated (Box 17)
  - Photographs, 1892-1992, undated; 8 (Box 17)
  - Oversize
    - Framed movie poster: John Barrymore in Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde, 1920 (Box 18)
    - John Barrymore estate auction poster; John Barrymore biography poster, 1942, undated (Box 18)
- November 2007 Acquisition, 1896-2000; 9.33; (12 boxes)
  The November 2007 Acquisition consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, printed and other materials relating to film, the Barrymore family, Leopold Stokowski, Ted Lewis, and other cultural figures and activities.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 993.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 24-25 (35mm film): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Gift of Eric H. Berger, 2007.
  - Spencer Berger collection, undated (Box 19)
  - Stokowski material, 1941-1996; 11 (Box 19)
  - Ted Lewis material, 1915-1997; 17 (Box 19)
  - Film correspondence 1970s, 1969-1979; 8 (Box 20)
  - Film correspondence 1980s, 1975-1988 (Box 20)
  - Film correspondence 1990s, 1989-1992 (Box 20)
  - Drew Barrymore, 19[85?]-1995, undated; 3 (Box 20)
  - Antoinette 9/22/91, 1972-1990 (Box 20)
  - Missing MP - Stills, 11/14/89, 1980-1989 (Box 20)
  - H of B pix to Knopf, 1990-1991 (Box 20)
  - Confessions and American 7/1987, 1933 (Box 20)
  - Barrymore, 1936-1983, undated (Box 20)
  - The Films of John Barrymore, 1921-1969 (Box 20)
  - J, E, and L 1920s and 30s, 1926-1988 (Box 20)
  - John Barrymore: A Centenary Tribute, 1982 July 6 (Box 20)
  - John Barrymore prints, 1932 (Box 20)
  - Article draft, 1957 (Box 20)
  - Barrymore, 1891-1991, undated; 2 (Box 20)
  - Richard III 1920, 1920-1940 (Box 20)
  - 1917, 1917 December 23 (Box 20)
  - 1916, 1916-1940 (Box 20)
  - Damned in Paradise, Kober, 1975-1988 (Box 20)
  - Streamlined Shakespeare, 1937, 1950 (Box 20)
  - 1915, 1915 September 5 (Box 20)
  - Lionel's reviews, 1927-1945 (Box 20)
  - Uncle Sam, 1911 (Box 20)
  - 1905, 1905 February 5 (Box 20)
  - Good Night Sweet Prince - G.F., 1940-1944 (Box 20)
  - Various papers, 1935-1990 (Box 20)
  - MP-10 - file, 1969-1990 (Box 20)
  - MP hold / future, 1944-1991 (Box 20)
  - Ethel - biography, 1940-1954 (Box 21)
  - 1941 (Box 21)
  - American Citizen, 1914-1952 (Box 21)
  - Fortune Hunter 1909, 1909-1940 (Box 21)
  - Twentieth Century 1934, 1934-1976 (Box 21)
  - Marie Antoinette 1938 (Box 21)
  - Thief for a Night 1913, 1913 April 1 (Box 21)
  - 1912 (Box 21)
  - Believe Me, Xantippe, 1913 (Box 21)
  - Misc., 1927-1928 (Box 21)
  - Bill of Divorcement, 1942-1956, undated (Box 21)
  - Spawn of the North, 1938, 1971 (Box 21)
  - 1938, 1938-1941 (Box 21)
  - Night Club Scandal, 1937 (Box 21)
  - True Confession, 1937 (Box 21)
  - Bulldog Dr.'s Revenge, 1937 (Box 21)
  - Long Lost Father, 1934 (Box 21)
  - 1933 (Box 21)
  - Topaze, 1933 (Box 21)
  - 1932 (Box 21)
  - 1930 (Box 21)
  - John Barrymore illness and death notices, 1942 (Box 21)
  - 1942, 1942-1943 (Box 21)
  - Bulldog Dr. Comes Back 1937 [empty], undated (Box 21)
  - 1939, 1939-1942 (Box 21)
  - 1921, 1921-1940 (Box 21)
  - Dinner at Eight, 1933, 1969 (Box 21)
  - Counsellor at Law, 1933-1970, undated (Box 21)
  - Rasputin, 1932-1971, undated (Box 21)
  - State's Attorney, 1932, undated (Box 21)
  - Arsene Lupin, 1932-1969 (Box 21)
  - Grand Hotel, 1932 (Box 21)
  - Svengali, 1931, undated (Box 21)
  - Mad Genius, 1931 (Box 21)
  - Moby Dick, 1930 (Box 21)
  - Show of Shows, 1930 (Box 21)
  - Man from Blankley's, 1930 (Box 21)
  - 1931 (Box 21)
  - 1935 (Box 21)
  - 1934 (Box 21)
  - 1936, 1936-1963 (Box 21)
  - Hold that Coed, 1938, 1968 (Box 21)
  - Bulldog Dr.'s Peril, 1938 (Box 21)
  - Romance in the Dark, 1938 (Box 21)
  - Midnight, 1939 (Box 21)
  - Great Man Votes, 1939-1940 (Box 21)
  - My Dear Children, 1938-1943 (Box 21)
  - World Premiere, 1941 (Box 21)
  - Playmates, 1941-1942 (Box 21)
  - The Great Profile, 1940 (Box 21)
  - The Invisible Woman, 1940-1941 (Box 21)
  - Articles for Saturday Review of Literature, 1944-1982 (Box 21)
  - Age 14 random notes, undated (Box 21)
  - Tribute to John Barrymore, 1969-1983 (Box 21)
  - SMB Keys [John Barrymore], 1982, undated (Box 21)
  - Titles, undated (Box 21)
  - Barrymore estate correspondence, 1942 (Box 21)
  - Misc. correspondence and drafts, 1957-1983 (Box 21)
  - Tribute to John Barrymore, 1969 (Box 21)
  - World of Entertainment 2/14/1982, JB Centennial (Box 21)
  - Sea Beast intro, 1953 May 14 (Box 21)
  - We Barrymores 5/1951, 1950-1952 (Box 21)
  - Wolper / John Barrymore biography, 1962-1963 (Box 21)
  - GEH John Barrymore tribute, 1969 (Box 21)
  - The Barrymores by Hollis Alpert, 1963-1965 (Box 21)
  - Yale Art Gallery 2/11/1982 JB centennial, 1982 February 8 (Box 21)
  - Tribute to John Barrymore, 1969 (Box 21)
  - Empty folders, undated (Box 21)
  - Barrymore, 1894-1997, undated; 20 (Box 22)
  - House of Barrymore, 1987-1989; 6 (Box 23)
  - Barrymore clippings, 1940-1988 (Box 23)
  - Articles, 1932-1936 (Box 23)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1955 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, notes and articles, 1914-1993 (Box 23)
  - Charlie McGee / Firestarter button, undated (Box 23)
  - 1920, 1920-1940 (Box 23)
  - 1919, 1919-1939 (Box 23)
  - 1918, 1918, 1942 (Box 23)
  - Redemption 1918, 1918-1940 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 1959, undated (Box 23)
  - Ethel Barrymore theatre program, circa 1929 (Box 23)
  - John Barrymore in The Beloved Rogue, undated (Box 23)
  - J. Barrymore moviebook, undated (Box 23)
  - My Dear Children tickets, 1940 (Box 23)
  - Photo-negatives New York Public Library, 1901-1918 (Box 23)
  - Maytime 1937 (Box 23)
  - Lubin, 9/87, 1980-1988 (Box 23)
  - File, 7/90, 1938-1988 (Box 23)
  - Sea Beast, 1973-1992 (Box 23)
  - Power-Waters biography, 1940-1941 (Box 23)
  - Barrymore reviews, 1919-1987 (Box 23)
  - Beinecke - Pat Willis 5/95, 1953-1993 (Box 23)
  - Barrymore clippings, 1936-1981 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence re film, 1914-1987 (Box 23)
  - Talks, articles, by SMB, 1953-1996 (Box 23)
  - Barrymore miscellaneous, 1913-1993, undated (Box 23)
  - "A Library of Motion Picture Stills Collected by Spencer Berger," canisters 1-30, 1903-1947, undated (Box 24 (Cold storage))
  - "A Library of Motion Picture Still Collected by Spencer Berger," canisters 31-42, 1903-1947, undated (Box 25 (Cold storage))
  - Scrapbook of Barrymore performances, undated
  - Ethel Barrymore Proofs, undated (Box 26)
  - Good Night Sweet Prince unrevised proofs, undated (Box 26)
  - The Barrymores (Albert, Hollis) proof, 1964 (Box 26)
  - Memoirs, Ethel Barrymore, 1954 December (Box 26)
  - Image magazine, 1973-1982; 6 (Box 27)
  - The Moonlighter, trade ad, 1953 June 17 (Box 27)
  - Lou Walters, Latin Quarter Program, 1946 August 3 (Box 27)
  - How to become a Movie Star, by Irving Klaw, 1946 (Box 27)
  - Films in Review, 1994 (Box 27)
  - Small Wonder program, 1948 August (Box 27)
  - The Smokies Guide; Great Smokey Mountains National Park, 1941 (Box 27)
  - Official Guidebook; Worlds Fair, Chicago, 1933 (Box 27)
  - Portrait photographs, 1973 (Box 27)
  - Misc. flyers, 1940-1942, undated (Box 27)
  - Misc. printed material, undated (Box 27)
  - The Films of Buster Keaton, 1969 April 18 (Box 27)
  - Bimini Bay Song, 1921 (Box 27)
  - Programs, 1915-1973 (Box 27)
  - Misc film - ? Beinecke, 1932-1985 (Box 27)
  - Shorts, surveys, personal, undated (Box 27)
  - Features 1935 on, undated (Box 27)
  - Records SMB films, undated (Box 27)
  - Kerr 9/93, 1974-1992 (Box 27)
  - Helen Claire, 1933-1974, undated (Box 27)
  - G. Fowler Letters, 1930-1977 (Box 27)
  - SMB Misc. correspondence, 1928-1991 (Box 27)
  - Jas.Card 12/94, 1950-2000 (Box 27)
  - Griggs Collection, 1944-1970; 2 (Box 27)
  - Weinberg, 1966-1979 (Box 27)
  - Flagg, 1937-1960 (Box 27)
  - K. Brownlow, 1970-1992 (Box 27)
  - Birchman, 1937-1943 (Box 28)
  - Vallee, 1975-1977 (Box 28)
  - Danny Kaye, 1975-1987; 3 (Box 28)
  - Tibbett, 1940-1976 (Box 28)
  - Woody Allen, 1978-1995 (Box 28)
  - SMB personal misc 8/96, 1941-1983 (Box 28)
  - Unpublished SMB film articles, 1976, undated (Box 28)
  - SMB lecture notes, 1953-1989 (Box 28)
  - Charlie Chaplin, 1977-1986 (Box 28)
  - Yale film course 12/66, 1965-1967, undated (Box 28)
  - Choate School Moby Dick, 1967 February 8 (Box 28)
  - Gaylord benefit program 4/01/73, 1972-1973 (Box 28)
  - N.H. Historical Society, 1966, 1982; 2 (Box 28)
  - World Entertainment Stokowski 4/18/1982, 1916-1982, undated (Box 28)
  - Don Juan - Creative Arts 2/22/1973, 1973 February (Box 28)
  - Western History Ass'n. 10-11-72, 1972-1974 (Box 28)
  - Butch Cassidy, 1969; 3 (Box 28)
  - SMB YAM article 2/1985, 1969-1995 (Box 28)
  - A.K. / Yale 10/1986, 1985-1987 (Box 28)
  - III-9 YFSC 5/1989, 1986-1990 (Box 28)
  - Yale Art Gallery, 1982 (Box 28)
  - YFA, 1969-1984; 2 (Box 28)
  - Film correspondence 1920s, 1927-1929 (Box 28)
  - Film correspondence 1930s, 1930-1939, undated; 2 (Box 28)
  - Film correspondence 1940s, 1936-1949; 3 (Box 28)
  - Film correspondence 1950s, 1934-1959; 3 (Box 28)
  - Film correspondence 1960s, 1946-1969; 2 (Box 28)
  - Correspondence and notes, 1909-1991; 5 (Box 28)
  - Film industry photos, 1901-1992, undated; 10 (Box 29)
  - Elizabeth Love Catron, 1936-1949 (Box 29)
  - Yale Film Associates, 1967-1973; 3 (Box 29)
  - Tibbett, 1930-1976 (Box 29)
  - Ted Lewis, 1970-1970, undated (Box 29)
  - Index to shorts, 1975-1982 (Box 29)
  - Misc. re: film, 1917-1981 (Box 29)
  - Sunday clips, programs, etc., 1937-1987, undated (Box 29)
  - Film at Yale, 1965-1988, undated (Box 29)
  - Beinecke, 1926-1983 (Box 29)
  - Acquisition data and catalog indices, undated (Box 29)
  - Oversize
    - Scrapbook of Barrymore performances, 1908-1941 (Box 30)
    - Walt Disney's Fantasia, 50th Anniversary commemorative program, undated (Box 30)
    - The Stage, 1933 June (Box 30)